Guide to the Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers, 1922-2007
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers
1922-2007
MssCol 17775
17775
Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
241.35 linear feet 570 boxes
The Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers document the life and work of Pulitzer Prize-winning American historian Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. (1917-2007), noted for his political activities in the Democratic Party and for his acclaimed accounts of nineteenth and twentieth century history. The collection consists of extensive correspondence, journals, writings, research material, office files and personal records. The papers provide insight into Schlesinger's philosophical, political, and historical thinking, while offering a glimpse of his daily activities. They represent Schlesinger's vocation as a popular and academic historian, as well as his life as a political activist and advisor.
Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. (1917-2007) was an American historian as renowned for his political activities as a liberal Democrat as for his critically acclaimed scholarly work. He won the Pulitzer Prize and National Book Award twice each, while playing a significant role in shaping the intellectual basis of postwar Democratic liberalism.
He was born Arthur Bancroft Schlesinger on October 15, 1917 to Arthur Meier Schlesinger and Elizabeth Bancroft Schlesinger, both well-known historians. Elizabeth was distantly related to historian George Bancroft. Born in Ohio, Schlesinger moved to Cambridge, Massachusetts when his father became a professor of history at Harvard University. Schlesinger changed his middle name to Meier when he was a teenager so as to share a name with his father. Graduating from Harvard University in 1938, Schlesinger eventually published his senior thesis on nineteenth-century theologian and activist Orestes Brownson. He studied at Cambridge University for a year, and then returned to Harvard as a research fellow, where he wrote The Age of Jackson (1945), which won him his first Pulitzer Prize. During World War II, he worked in the Office of War Information and the Office of Strategic Services, a forerunner of the Central Intelligence Agency. In 1946, he returned to Harvard as an assistant professor of history. Despite not having a doctorate, Schlesinger had completed Harvard's own research fellowship program, and his academic career was never adversely affected by his choice not to pursue a doctoral degree. Schlesinger helped found the Americans for Democratic Action (ADA), a leading anti-Communist liberal group, in 1947.
Active in Democratic Party politics in Massachusetts, as well as at the national level, Schlesinger was heavily involved in Averell Harriman's campaign for the 1952 Democratic presidential nomination. When Harriman left the race, Schlesinger offered his services to Adlai Stevenson, forging a friendship and political alliance that would last for many years. Schlesinger wrote speeches, made appearances, and provided political advice to Stevenson in both his 1952 and 1956 presidential campaigns. Once sure that Stevenson was not planning to run for the office in 1960, Schlesinger aligned himself with Senator John F. Kennedy, a friend from Massachusetts. After helping to elect Kennedy in 1960, Schlesinger was appointed a special assistant to the President in 1961. He took an extended leave of absence from Harvard University to join the Kennedy Administration, where he worked as a problem solver, Latin American expert, and unofficial liaison to the academic community. Initially under the impression that Kennedy did not intend him to write the history of his presidency, Schlesinger later felt that he was expected to keep detailed notes on what he saw and heard. After President Kennedy's assassination, Schlesinger stayed on briefly during the transitional period of the Johnson Administration. He left the White House in early 1964, never to return to full-time work in the political realm. He did, however, serve as a speechwriter and advisor in the presidential campaigns of Robert F. Kennedy in 1968 and George S. McGovern in 1972. His final active role in a political campaign was with Senator Edward M. Kennedy in his quest for the Democratic presidential nomination in 1980, although he did provide advice to Bill Clinton and Al Gore during their presidential campaigns.
His account of the Kennedy White House, A Thousand Days (1965), won him his second Pulitzer Prize. Among his other important historical works are the three-volume history of the New Deal, The Age of Roosevelt (1957-1960); The Imperial Presidency (1973); Robert F. Kennedy and His Times (1978), for which he won the National Book Award; The Cycles of American History (1986); The Disuniting of America (1992) and his memoir A Life in the 20th Century: Innocent Beginnings, 1917-1950 (2000). He always hoped to continue the Age of Roosevelt series after his service in Washington, but never wrote the planned fourth volume.
Schlesinger became the Albert Schweitzer Professor of Humanities at the City University of New York in 1966. He settled in Manhattan, where he remained until his death, sharing a fence with neighbor Richard M. Nixon at one point. During his years in New York he led a remarkably active social and political life, associating and collaborating with a broad range of academic, political, and cultural figures, while continuing to articulate his distinctive and historically-informed opinions through books, articles, book and movie reviews, lectures and speeches, petitions, and newspaper editorials.
Schlesinger married twice and had six children. His first marriage, to Marian Cannon, ended in divorce in 1969, and his second marriage, to Alexandra Emmet, lasted until the end of his life. He had two sons and two daughters from his first marriage, and a son and stepson from his second.
Portions of the collection had previously been on deposit at the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum. Material deposited in 1968 and 1969, focusing primarily but not exclusively on Schlesinger's time in the White House, remains at the Kennedy Library. Material deposited from 1980 forward has all been incorporated into this collection.
The Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers, dating from 1922-2007, document the historian's life and work through extensive correspondence, journals, writings, research material, office files and personal records. The papers provide insight into Schlesinger's philosophical, political, and historical thinking, while offering a glimpse of his daily activities. The collection represents Schlesinger's vocation as a popular and academic historian, as well as his life as a political activist and advisor. Every era of Schlesinger's life and career appear in the collection; however, much of the material generated by Schlesinger as part of the Kennedy Administration is held by the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum. The holdings of the Kennedy Library include correspondence, subject files, speech files, and telephone logs from Schlesinger's tenure at the White House. Research material for A Thousand Days, as well as various drafts of the book, can also be found among the Schlesinger papers at the Kennedy Library. Nineteen boxes of alphabetical correspondence unrelated to the Kennedy Administration, spanning the years 1945-1960, are held by the Kennedy Library; researchers seeking a complete record of Schlesinger's personal and professional correspondence should be prepared to search the Kennedy Library's collection also.
Schlesinger's correspondence spans almost his entire life, beginning when he was first learning to write, and continuing to his death. He corresponded with friends, acquaintances, colleagues, readers, publishers, editors, and relatives. The collection illustrates the often fluid nature of those categories, as Schlesinger often combined friendship with professional and political association. Schlesinger maintained his correspondence according to a variety of filing systems kept in separate offices, and the collection contains letters organized alphabetically, chronologically, and by subject. Since Schlesinger did not use a single consistent means of filing, researchers should consider all the correspondence subseries, as well as relevant writings (in Series III) and research files (in Series IV), when seeking out a particular subject, era, or individual.
The journals chronicle most of Schlesinger's adult life, spanning fifty years beginning in the early 1950s. The time between entries ranges from one day to several months, and the number of pages devoted to a given year ranges from sixty to over four hundred. Schlesinger used his journal to describe meetings, political events, and social engagements; he also frequently expressed his political insights and opinions when writing. An edited compilation of the journals was published posthumously. (Journals, 1952-2000 by Arthur M. Schlesinger; edited by Andrew Schlesinger and Stephen Schlesinger. New York: Penguin Press, 2007.)
The collection includes many unpublished writings, such as lectures, speeches, eulogies, and commencement addresses; drafts of published writings include those of Robert Kennedy and His Times (see Series IV), as well as some article drafts with related correspondence in Series IV.
As a historian and political commentator, Schlesinger was a careful and prodigious researcher. He maintained research files on his full-length works (The Age of Roosevelt, The Age of Jackson and Robert Kennedy and His Times included here), as well as subject files for other writings. The files include clippings, research notes, interviews, correspondence, and student papers.
The collection includes files on Schlesinger's family and various eras of his own life. These include schoolwork, scrapbooks, photographs, legal documents, and documentation from his service in World War II. The papers also contain copies of Schlesinger's F.B.I. files, obtained via the Freedom of Information Act., found in Series V.
Finally, the collection contains appointment books and phone message logs, illustrating the details of Schlesinger's daily activities from the early 1950s onward.
The Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. Papers are organized in the following series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1923-2007
Series II: Journals, circa 1930; 1950-2003
Series III: Writings, 1946-2005
Series IV: Research Files
Series V: Personal and Family Files, 1922-2007
Series VI: Appointment Books and Telephone Messages, 1951-2004
Purchased from the Estate of Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr.
Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. and Gilbert Seldes correspondence. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. papers. John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum (http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Archives+and+Manuscripts/fa_schlesinger.htm).
Advance notice required.
Sound and video recordings are unavailable for use pending preservation transfer. Journals may not be photocopied. Restricted correspondence to be made available in 2050. Classified research material restricted pending government declassification.
Selections from the journals were published in 2007 as Journals, 1952-2000 by Penguin Press
Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989; Berlin, Isaiah, 1909-1997; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-2006; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Rauh, Joseph L., 1911-; Tree, Marietta, 1917-1991; Americans for Democratic Action; Century Club (New York, N.Y.); City University of New York; Democratic Party (U.S.); Harvard University; Political campaigns -- United States; appointment books; Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings; United States -- History -- 1945-; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1945-1970; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1971-; College teachers -- United States; Historians -- United States; Journalists -- United States
- Series I: Correspondence, 1923-2007; 384760; 286 boxes
  This series represents a lifetime of communication, both personal and professional. Beginning in his childhood during the 1920s and continuing to the end of his life, Schlesinger's correspondence traces his relationships and activities in the political, literary and academic spheres. The series includes correspondence with friends, colleagues, publishers and organizations, on a variety of subjects ranging from the frivolity of Schlesinger's personal fashion to the gravity of war and political regime change. The spectrum of correspondents reflects the wide-ranging nature of Schlesinger's acquaintanceship. There are letters to and from sitting presidents of the United States, as well as noted intellectuals, authors, critics, government officials, Supreme Court justices, celebrities, students and fans. Schlesinger was always eager to share ideas, and the volume and quality of the letters in this series provide insight into the views of Schlesinger and his friends and associates.
  Schlesinger's correspondence from the late 1940s onward was usually sent through an office and secretary, but there are also many examples of letters written or typed by Schlesinger himself. As Schlesinger maintained numerous correspondence files at both his home and CUNY offices, and these files were organized in different ways, researchers should examine all of the correspondence subseries, as the same correspondent may appear in the alphabetical, chronological and/or subject correspondence. Related correspondence can also be found in Series III and Series IV. Apart from the chronological office file (Subseries C), all of the subseries herein contain a combination of incoming and outgoing letters, with Schlesinger's replies often attached to incoming letters. A file of restricted correspondence will become available in 2050 and a file of presidential memoranda will become available as it is declassified.
  Much of Schlesinger's office correspondence from 1961-1963 is absent from the collection, to be found in the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum. The Kennedy Library also possesses a file of alphabetical correspondence from the fifteen years preceding Schlesinger's 1961 White House appointment. Since the Kennedy Library holdings overlap chronologically with this collection, researchers seeking the complete correspondence of a given period, or between Schlesinger and a particular individual, may well have to visit both repositories. The Kennedy Library's finding aid for its Schlesinger papers can be viewed here: http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Archives+and+Manuscripts/fa_schlesinger.htm
  - Subseries I.A. Alphabetical correspondence, 1934-2006; 384761; 150 boxes
    This subseries incorporates alphabetical correspondence files maintained in Schlesingers apartment and in separate home and City University of New York offices, and are arranged by correspondent. Individual names predominate, but there are some organizational correspondents as well. As a result of the combination of files, there is some degree of alphabetical overlap across folders. In the case of folders representing spans of letters, the folders have been alphabetized by the first letter or cluster of letters (e.g., Bor-Bri precedes Boy-Bra). Researchers seeking a particular correspondent may need to check more than one folder. Although most of the correspondence is arranged by name within the general alphabetical files, Schlesinger would occasionally maintain separate files for particular correspondents. However, a separate file for an individual does not preclude the presence of letters from that person in the broader alphabetical files. With few exceptions, the original order within each folder has been retained. The majority of the alphabetical correspondence dates from the 1960s onward, but there is a significant amount from the 1940s and 1950s as well.
    While many correspondents are represented by only a letter or two, there are some whose exchanges with Schlesinger continued over decades. Noted economist John Kenneth Galbraith, for example, was one of Schlesingers closest friends, dating back to their meeting at Harvard in the 1930s, and they kept in close touch through the years, even after they were no longer neighbors in Massachusetts. Another Harvard friendship bloomed with Felix Frankfurter, and Schlesingers correspondence with him continued through Frankfurters time on the Supreme Court.
    Other long-term friends corresponding with Schlesinger included columnist Joseph Alsop, civil libertarian and lawyer Joseph Rauh, and Ambassador William J. vanden Heuvel. As with many of Schlesingers friends in the intellectual and political realms, they were all closely allied with liberal politics at the time. As a founding member of the Americans for Democratic Action (ADA), Schlesinger developed many lasting friendships with liberal, though staunchly anti-Communist, politicians and intellectuals like himself. Reinhold Niebuhr, the influential theologian who combined a liberal political viewpoint with deeply held religious convictions, was another founding member of the ADA, and Schlesinger corresponded with him often, considering Niebuhr one of the great minds of the century.
    Although Schlesingers ties to liberal politics and the Democratic Party kept him in regular contact with people who shared his opinions, he had friends and acquaintances who had vastly different world views. Conservative icon William F. Buckley, Jr. was a longtime friend whose correspondence with Schlesinger refers not just to their occasional public appearances together in debates or on television, but also to their social relationship.
    In some cases, an individuals correspondence with Schlesinger shows a change in their relationship over time. Hubert Humphrey, the liberal senator noted for his legislative success, was a close associate of Schlesingers, pursuing many of the same political goals in the 1940s and 1950s. In the 1960s, however, when the two drifted apart as a result of Humphreys positions while serving as Vice President and Schlesingers support of other candidates against him, their correspondence vividly illustrates the split. In contrast, Schlesingers relationship with author Rebecca West began with a heated exchange of insulting letters about a published comment of his, and then matured into a close friendship between the two writers and their families.
    Other frequent and significant correspondents in this subseries include Max Ascoli, Isaiah Berlin, McGeorge Bundy, Bernard DeVoto, Averell Harriman, Mary McCarthy, George McGovern, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Richard Rovere, Gilbert Seldes, Theodore Sorensen, Marietta Tree, Sacha Volman, James Wechsler, Morton White and Charles Wintour.
    - A, 384762 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - A-Ad, 384763 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A-Ak, 384764 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - A-Al, 384765 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1967-1970; 384766 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ag-Ap, 384767 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Al-Aq, 384768 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Alsop, Joseph, 1947-1990; 384769 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Am-Ar, 384770 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Amalrik, Andrei, 1960, 1970-1971; 384771 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - American Academy & Institute of Arts and Letters, 1966-1981; 384772 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - American Book Awards, 1984-1985; 384773 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1971-1982; 384774 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - American Committee for Cultural Freedom, 1951-1955; 384775 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Americans for Democratic Action, 384776
      - 1966-1969, 384777 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1970-1982, 384778 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - American Film Institute, 1966-1976; 384779 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
    - American Heritage/WGBH, 1973-1982; 384780 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - American Historical Association, 1969-1982; 384781 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Annan, Kofi, 2001-2002; 384782 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Ar-Ay, 384783 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ar-Az, 384784 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - As-Bal, 384785 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Ascoli, Max, 1949-2001; 384786 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1971-1981; 384787 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, 1966-1977; 384788 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Auchincloss, Louis, 1994; 384789 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - B, 384790 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Ba-Bal, 384791 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Ba-Bav, 384792 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Ba-Bd, 384793 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bacall, Lauren, 1999-2002; 384794 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ball, George W., 1966-1994; 384795 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ban-Bat, 384796 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Ban-Ber, 384797 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Bau-Bel, 384798 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Be-Ben, 384799 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Be-Bev, 384800 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Be-Bk, 384801 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Beard, Charles, 1942-1943; 384802 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Beatty, Warren, 1998; 384803 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Beck, Emily M., 1966-1980; 384804 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Bem-Bev, 384805 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Benton, William, 1966-1973; 384806 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Berle, Adolph and Beatrice, 1966-1987; 384807 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Berlin, Isaiah, 1952-1995; 384808 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
    - Bes-Boo, 384809 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Bia-Bin, 384810 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Bia-Bis, 384811 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Bin-Bla, 384812 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Bingham, Jonathan, 1966-1994; 384813 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Bl, 384814 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Bl-Bt, 384815 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Bla-Bly, 384816 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Bloch, Ann, 1934-1937; 384817 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Bloom, Claire, 2002; 384818 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Blum, John, 1961-1994; 384819 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Bo-Boy, 384820 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Boa-Box, 384821 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Bor-Bri, 384822 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Boy-Bra, 384823 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Bra-Bri, 384824 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Braden, Thomas W., 1966-1975; 384825 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Bre-Bro, 384826 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Breyer, Stephen, 2002; 384827 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Bro-Brow, 384828 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Bro-Buc, 384829 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Brogan, D.W., 1943; 384830 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Brokaw, Tom, 1998-1999; 384831 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Brown-Broza, 384832 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Brown, Denise, 1984; 384833 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Brown, Helen Gurley, 1998; 384834 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Bru-By, 384835 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Bru-Bz, 384836 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Bu-Bz, 384837 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Buchwald, Art, 2006; 384838 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Buckley, William F., 1967-2001; 384839 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Buh-By, 384840 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Bumpers, Dale, 1998; 384841 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1954-1994; 384842 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Bundy, Mary, 2004; 384843 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Burns, James McGregor, 1966-1990; 384844 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Bush, George H. W., 1970-1992; 384845 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Buxton, Moira E., 1969-1971; 384846 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Byrd, Robert, 2004; 384847 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - C, 384848 (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
    - Ca-Ch, 384849 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Cab-Car, 384850 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Cab-Cav, 384851 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Cad-Car, 384852 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Canfield, Cass, 1966-1981; 384853 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Car-Cha, 384854 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 2002; 384855 (Box 23, Folder 4)